Good morning. Today's דף Daf is דף כ"ח, Daf Kaf Ches, and
which is a little bit of a challenging דף, Daf, so everybody's
got to hold cup. It's really an explication of the משנה Mishnah
that we ended with yesterday on כ"ז עמוד ב', Kaf Zayin Amud
Beis, which listed those who are פסול Pasul because of a קורבה,
Korva, because of familial relation. And the basic principle to repeat it
was well, what the משנה Mishnah mentioned was the משנה Mishnah basically
mentioned cases of uncle, was a prime case, brother and uncle, and
then it included those relatives and uncle could be a number of
ways: father's brother, father's sister's husband, mother's brother, mother's sister's
husband, okay, all different forms of uncle and that's based on a
principle also like we basically assume type of an אשתו כגופו, Ishto
Kigufo, if you're related, then married is sort of gets consecrated as
one unit. And then it says those people, brothers and uncles, and
their sons, so that would mean for brother's son, it's a nephew,
which we already implicitly had by uncle, but an uncle's son is
a first cousin, and even their sons-in-law, again based on this sort
of principle of אשתו כגופו. Ishto Kigufo. So your first cousin by
marriage,
the man married to your first cousin, to your first cousin who's
a woman, is also פסול. Pasul. Okay, so that's basically the range
of פסולים, Psulim, and that in הלכה Halacha terminology is if
brothers, here's ראובן Reuven and שמעון, Shimon, okay, this is ראשון בראשון,
Rishon Berishon, they're like the same generation, then ראובן Reuven's son is
חנוך, Chanoch, okay, so that would be, so this relationship would be
a ראשון בשני Rishon Besheini or a שני בראשון, Sheini Berishon, and
שמעון Shimon's son, Michael, what was it, נמואל, Nemuel, thank you, excellent,
נמואל, Nemuel, so a first cousin is שני בשני. Sheini Besheini. Okay,
and again, if let's say he has a daughter, which is, I
don't know, called גיטל, Gittel, okay, and married to a guy here,
מרדכי, Mordechai, outside of the family, okay, that's also like a שני
בראשון Sheini Berishon or a שני בשני Sheini Besheini and so on.
Okay, those are the relations mentioned in the משנה, Mishnah, and then
it said oh and also it said, the other case mentioned was
a גיסו, Giso, which was a brother-in-law, okay, so שמעון Shimon's wife
here,
חנוך Chanoch and מרדכי, Mordechai, right, is
that,
yeah, okay fine, if you want to look here and ignore this
generation, so this is a גיס, Gis, this is a brother-in-law, okay,
and even if גיטל, Gittel, and even if you know, so that
would be right, your sister's, right, you know your sister's husband, but
it could even be a case about a case about your, what
do you call it, your wife's sister's husband, so that would be
even a further case. So if שמעון Shimon here was married to,
I don't know,
לאה, Leah, and לאה Leah's sister was רחל, Rachel, and רחל Rachel
here was married to, I don't know, עזרא, Ezra, okay, so this
case is also a case of brother-in-law, right, even though it's like
two in-laws, right, your wife's sister's husband, okay, that's גיסו, Giso, that's
also included, but it's essentially a type of a brother. All right,
and then and all of those would include, again, the brother and
the uncle would include the next generation. So that would include, so
if you looked at here, right, so שמעון Shimon would be פסול
Pasul not only to עזרא, Ezra, but to עזרא Ezra's son or
son-in-law. Okay, so this is a case of גיס, Gis, which is
a type of brother law, and it had חורגו, Chorgo, which is
a stepson. All right, so we'll worry about stepson later, but the
one exception in the משנה Mishnah is that by your stepson, you're
not אסור Assur in terms of your stepson's son or son-in-law. Okay,
so because stepson there's like, so that's like, זה רבי
שמעון בן הקני.
Ze
Rabbi Shimon Ben Hakannai.
There you go, yes. Just like a math kind of thing. Okay,
so the לאה Leah and רחל Rachel are like whatever, a zero
or a different color or something, right, so they don't count and
therefore שמעון Shimon and עזרא Ezra are like brothers.
Right,
right, but it's because, I mean rather than saying they don't count,
but it's like a type of an אשתו כגופו, Ishto Kigufo, this
like counts as one unit and this counts as one unit. Right.
Yeah, yeah, yes, yes, that's the basic point. It doesn't make it
further removed. Now there are some times in הלכה Halacha where, and
this is not going to come up explicitly in this גמרא, Gemara,
but just so you know, which is a principle called we always
say one אשתו כגופו, Ishto Kigufo, do we say two אשתו כגופו?
Ishto Kigufo? Okay, so if it's, this would be a case of
two אשתו כגופו Ishto Kigufo where you have to do, do the
women combine them twice? And sometimes we do when it's a close
relationship, when it's like all at a brother level, but if it's
like, if it was... Shimon's sister's daughter's son, okay, you might not
sort of say like two אשתו כגופו, Ishto kegufo, but I don't
want to bother that. Okay, but this is basically the principle of
שני בשני. Sheni besheni. That's how far we get, שני בשני, Sheni
besheni, first cousins including in-laws, okay. That's the basic principle of the
Mishna. And then the Mishna went on to cases about if it's
a relationship through marriage and the woman died, that then they would
stop being קרובים Krovim and so on. That's a later concern. Yes.
Does that mean that the women cannot be witnesses?
It's just... Right, that's taken for granted that the women cannot be
witnesses.
Now, what was... Right. What?
What did you say? Yeah, but that's not relevant. Right. Now, the
other thing is, is again the sort of parenthetical point that a
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose made that this is רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva
teaching, because רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, because all of these include relationships
that you could argue are through women. First of all, these are,
you know, cases of אשתו כגופו Ishto kegufo could be through women,
but also, you know, here I've got like a lot of men,
but like case of an uncle
could also be, you know, חנוך, Chanoch, you know, whatever. ראובן's Reuven
wife, I don't know what we'll call her, anyway, רבקה, Rivka, okay.
So, no, ראובן's, Reuven excuse me, not wives, ראובן's, Reuven I don't
know, let's say, no, ראובן's, Reuven yeah, no, yeah, חנוך's Chanoch mother,
let's say חנוך's Chanoch mother was רבקה Rivka and רבקה's Rivka brother.
Okay, I don't know who רבקה's Rivka brother is, but anyway, לוי,
Levi, whatever. Okay, so in this type of a case, okay, the
Mishna included uncles and whatever where there were women in the whole
thing. It could be your uncle on your mother's side, right? It
could be your mother's sister's husband and whatever. And because there are
all these mothers and women and so on, they're relationships that not
only are in the line of inheritance. Okay, so this all has
to just do with degree of removal, and women are included and
not in the line of inheritance. So that's רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva
teaching. But רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says that the earlier teaching was
the only one you're פסול Pasul for is somebody up to this
generation, uncle and cousin, but only someone you can inherit from. And
you can't testify for them because if you testify for them, let's
say on their behalf, and they win a million dollar lawsuit, well,
you might be eventually the יורש. Yoresh. Okay, so that's what the
earlier teaching was. Yes, it was limited to uncles and cousins, but
it didn't basically always go through women and mothers because it was
limited to ראוי לירושה. Ra'ui liyerusha.
Does it even mean right now, not like you actually would? Right.
Correct. Correct. Exactly.
Exactly. But it wouldn't be any theoretical יורש Yoresh because then it
could be a million generations, okay. So it agreed that it was
up to cousins, but only it was a subset of this, only
this group of people if you were in a line of inheritance.
Okay, alright, so that's the basic principle.
But the one in the next generation that we said are not,
are able to be witnesses, they're still in a line of inheritance.
Right, so that's what I said. It's not anybody in a line
of inheritance. It's not like those stories about, you know, there's a
case like within the English royalty that a guy was like hundred
and tenth in the line of being of like the king and
he went about trying to kill everybody between him.
There's a play like that, but there's actually a historical case that
was like that.
And anyway, it was the seventh or
something, pretty much like that. Okay, anyway. So there, okay, anyway, so
it's not everybody who's... okay, but within this, it's a subset of
this. But that's the earlier teaching. Let's take a look at the
Gemara. מנא הני מילי? Mena hani mili? Where is this from? דתנו
רבנן. Detanu rabanan. לא יומתו אבות על בנים. Lo yumtu avot al
banim. מה תלמוד לומר? Ma talmud lomar? What does that mean? That
fathers shouldn't die on account of their sons, and sons on the
account of their fathers. אם ללמד שלא יומתו אבות בעוון בנים, Im
lelamed shelo yumtu avot be'avon banim, that they don't get punished for
the sin of their children, ובנים בעוון אבות, Uvanim be'avon avot, and
children don't get punished for the sin of their fathers, הרי כבר
נאמר, Harei kvar neemar, that we know, איש בחטאו יומתו, Ish bechet'o
yumatu, the end of it, each person dies on their own sin.
אלא לא יומתו אבות על בנים בעדות בנים, Ela lo yumtu avot
al banim be'edut banim, they can't die by the testimony of their
sons. ובנים לא יומתו על אבות בעדות אבות. Uvanim lo yumtu al
avot be'edut avot. Now, because it says, what's implicit here is because
אבות Avot is in the plural, we're going to sort of say
that that refers to, I'm just going to erase some, just for
simplicity's sake, okay, לא יומתו אבות, Lo yumtu avot, these are two
fathers. Again, how we know they're brothers I don't know, but this
but they can't die על בנים, Al banim, so somehow that includes
not only a son and a father, but a son, like a
child and his father's brother. These are the אבות Avot in the
plural. Okay, you just have to
take it on faith that אבות Avot here assumes that they're fathers
who are brothers. Alright, so anyway, so that's how we know that
idea. Okay. ובנים באבות. Uvanim be'avot. והכתיב, Vehakhtiv, the Gemara says, now
the Gemara digresses for a minute. ובנים לא יומתו על אבות בעדות
אבות. Uvanim lo yumtu al avot be'edut avot. ובנים בעוון אבות לא?
Uvanim be'avon avot lo? והכתיב פוקד
עוון אבות על בנים? Vehakhtiv poked avon avot al banim? What do
you mean? We have a principle that God does visit the iniquity
of the fathers on the children. התם כשאוחזין מעשה אבותיהם בידיהם. Hatam
keshe'ochazin ma'aseh avoteihem bi'yedeihem. That's when they continue in the deeds of
their fathers. כדתניא, Kedatanya, ואף בעוונות אבותם אתם ימקו. Ve'af ba'avonot avotam
itam yimaku. This is by the קללה, Klala, they will waste... by
the sins of their fathers כשאוחזין מעשה אבותיהם בידיהם keshe'ochzin ma'aseh avoteihem
biyadeihem when they continue in their paths. את אומר כשאוחזין או אינו
אלא כשאין אוחזין? At omer keshe'ochzin o eino ela keshein ochzin? Maybe
even if they don't continue in their paths? כשהוא אומר איש בחטאו
יומתו, keshehu omer ish becheto yumatu, they will only die in their
own sins, הרי כשאוחזין מעשה אבותיהם בידיהם. harei keshe'ochzin ma'aseh avoteihem biyadeihem.
Okay, so that's an interesting theological point which we are not going
to explore because we have enough to work with right now in
terms of the הלכה halakhah issues. Okay, ובלאו הכי, u'belav hachi,
now really? You're telling me that you don't suffer for somebody else's
sin even if you're not if you don't follow their ways? But
doesn't it say וכשלו איש באחיו, vekhashlu ish be'achiv, one man will
stumble over his brother, איש בעוון אחיו, ish ba'avon achiv, that they'll
stumble over the sins of their brothers, they'll be held accountable for
somebody else's sin? And that's not even a father and a child,
that's one person and a fellow person. מלמד שכולם ערבים זה בזה,
melamed shekulam arevim zeh bazeh, they are all, you know, everybody is
a co-guarantor
for everybody else, that if you're that, you know, if somebody sins
and that, you know, then God will come and exact the punishment
from you, you are you have to make sure that that person
everybody else is responsible for everybody's responsible for everybody else that they're
living up to their obligations. התם שהיה בידם למחות ולא מיחו. Hatam
shehayah beyadam limchot velo michu. Yes,
but that is only if you could have done something about it.
You could have protested and the protesting would have done some good
and you chose not to. But if there was nothing you could
have done about it, you won't be held responsible. That's not just
a metaphysical accounting, that's because in actual there's a degree of blame
and fault that you had a responsibility and you could have done
something about it. Okay, so that's all very interesting in terms of
context of responsibility for other people's sins, but that's not our focus.
Now, עד כאן אבות לבנים ובנים לאבות. ad kan avot lebanim ubanim
le'avot. So we have found now the idea of sons and fathers
and again just take it on faith here that the אבות avot
in plural means also uncles. So that we get, but וכל שכן
אבות להדדי vechol sheken avot lahadadi בנים. banim. So certainly,
one minute, ובנים לאבות וכל שכן אבות להדדי, ubanim le'avot vechol sheken
avot lahadadi,
thank you, אבות להדדי. avot lahadadi. So if you can't have a
בן ben to an אב, av, meaning to an uncle, the אבות
avot means again they're related, then certainly you can't have brothers. Okay,
'cause once I if you can't do a nephew to an uncle
then you certainly can't have uncles. בנים לבנים מנלן? banim lebanim minalan?
How do you know you can't have the sons of the fathers,
cousins? How do you know you extend it to a cousin? Okay,
so אם כן לכתוב קרא לא יומתו אבות על בן. im ken
lichtov kra lo yumtu avot al ben. So then just say two
fathers, one son. That gets you the father, son and brothers and
uncles. So מאי בנים? mai banim? Sons? So the sons of those
fathers who are brothers also can't testify on one another. So דאפילו
בנים להדדי. dafilu banim lahadadi. So that gets you cousins. עד כאן
בנים להדדי. ad kan banim lahadadi. So that's cousins, brothers to one
another,
sons of fathers who are brothers. בנים לעלמא מנלן? banim le'alma minalan?
Now, that's I can't testify against or for my cousin, but how
do I know that two cousins can't testify about somebody else? Okay,
that's a different
idea. So אמר רמי בר חמא, amar Rami bar Chama, סברא. sevara.
No, that's just סברא. sevara. כדתניא, kedetanya, I'll give you a case
where essentially testifying about somebody else is effectively testifying about one another.
How is that true? כדתניא אין עדים זוממים נהרגים עד שיזומו שניהם.
kedetanya ein edim zomemim neheragim ad sheyizomu shenehem. So עדים זוממים edim
zomemim until both of them are found זוממים. zomemim.
Okay, so let'say these cousins here, חנוך Chanoch and נמואל, Nemuel, testify
there against Michael. And then came two witnesses and said you guys
both were with us at בפניא דההוא יומא, Befanya de'hahu yoma, you're
both עדים זוממים. edim zomemim. Okay, fine. Now why is it going
to be relevant? דאי סלקא דעתך בנים לעלמא כשירים, de'i salka datach
banim le'alma keshirim, now if they could have testified here against Michael,
נמצא עד זומם נהרג בעדות אחיו. nimtza ed zomem neherag be'edut achiv.
So here they were, so it won't be Michael because it was
a capital case, wouldn't be, so they testified against somebody that was
חייב chayav a capital crime. They were proven to be זוממים. zomemim.
And now they're going to get put to death. So why is
חנוך Chanoch going to get put to death? Part of the reason
חנוך Chanoch is going to get put to death, in addition to
the fact that he testified falsely and he was an עד זומם,
ed zomem, is because of the testimony of נמואל. Nemuel. If if
it hadn't been for the false testimony of נמואל Nemuel or the
testimony of נמואל Nemuel all together, he would have gotten off the
hook. You can't make him an עד זומם...
ed zomem... you're doing this to kill this innocent guy?
Yeah, but
without two people testifying and both of them being found זוממים, zomemim,
you don't get punished. That's just the גזירת הכתוב. gezerat hakatuv. Correct.
We'll worry about that more in מכות, Makkot, but that is correct.
Okay, maybe it's מלקות malkut for
עד שקר. ed sheker. Okay, so anyway, so נמואל's Nemuel testimony was
was, you know, was necessary for getting חנוך Chanoch killed. And חנוך's
Chanoch testimony was getting... so now יומתו אבות על בנים. yumtu avot
al banim.
Their testimony led is bringing about the death of their co-עד. ed.
Okay, so it's a little bit of a stretch, which the גמרא
Gemara is going to say. נמצא עד זומם נהרג בעדות אחיו. nimtza
ed zomem neherag be'edut achiv. So אמר ליה רבא, amar leh Rava,
so רבא Rava said, ותימיך u'temeich one minute. According to that logic,
הדתנן, Hadatnan, שלשה אחים באחד מצטרף עמהן הרי אלו ג' עדויות. Sheloshah
achim b'echad mitztaref imahen harei elu gimmel eduyot. You have three brothers,
each one saw somebody. Remember the בבא בתרא Bava Batra years of
חזקה? Chazakah? So each one of these brothers, ראובן Reuven saw the
guy have one year of eating, שמעון Shimon saw him eat the
second year, לוי Levi saw him eat the third year, and then
a fourth guy who wasn't related to any of them, מרדכי, Mordechai,
he saw this guy eat all three years. So מרדכי Mordechai and
ראובן Reuven are a good כת Kat of עדים edim that he
ate year one. מרדכי Mordechai and שמעון Shimon are a good כת
Kat of עדים edim that he ate year two. And מרדכי Mordechai
and לוי Levi are a good כת Kat of עדים edim that
he ate year three. And the brothers, it's not a problem of
brothers testifying together because each brother testified on a different year. Okay,
so הרי אלו ג' עדויות, Harei elu gimmel eduyot, those are three
separate testimonies and it all works. ואין עדות אחת להזמה, V'ein edut
achat l'hazamah, but if somebody comes and says you're all, you're all
lying and you're all עדים זוממים, Edim zomemim, you have to prove
that everybody is a false witness because if only one or two,
then the effect of their testimony, if they're saying that you ate
these years like Michal's land, if only, if only two of those
years are proven to be false testimony, then the, the effect of
that testimony would not have awarded you the land. You needed the
total effect, the cumulative effect of all sets of the witnesses to
have attested to three years. So for all of those people to
be found, to for them to be found עדים זוממים, Edim zomemim,
all three groups, which is really three brothers plus מרדכי, Mordechai, have
to all be proven זוממין Zomemin for them to be עדים זוממים.
Edim zomemim. Okay, got the, got the scenario?
If they're found זוממין, Zomemin, yeah, then, then doesn't he lose the
חזקה? Chazakah?
What?
Yes. So once one is זוממין, Zomemin, right, then, then David here
would lose the חזקה. Chazakah. Okay, but they, but they, but until
all three are זוממים, Zomemim, they don't have to go ahead and
you don't do ועשיתם לו כאשר זמם, Va'asitem lo ka'asher zamam, because
then they don't, what their testimony doesn't have the effect of taking
the land away from you unless all three groups are זוממים. Zomemim.
But as soon as one is removed, he loses his חזקה. Chazakah.
That is correct. Okay.
If one individual who was seen paired up with all the other
three brothers
was proved to be a זומם? Zomem? Then again, everybody, everything will
get thrown out. But until, but until, you know, until the effect
of the entire effect of the testimony is proven זומם, Zomem, then
you don't have the principle that here they were, they were trying
to hurt Michal. Okay, because if only one group is a זומם,
Zomem, then this group, this thing by itself wasn't hurting Michal. Only
this and this and this was hurting Michal. So they only have
to go ahead and, you know, and pay Michal the plot of
land what they were trying to do to hurt only if everybody
was a זומם. Zomem. Okay.
You mean you have to prove both or just one
in the, and one in the כת? Kat? One, one neutralizes the
עדות, Edut, but both to make them pay. Both to punish them.
Okay. אין עדים נעשים זוממים עד שיזומו שניהם. Ein edim na'asim zomemim
ad she'yizumu shneihem. They all have to be proven זוממים, Zomemim, okay,
and if there's multiple components, it all has to be זומם Zomem
in order to make them pay. All right, but one is enough
to get it dismissed. Okay, so in that case, ואין עדות אחת
להזמה. V'ein edut achat l'hazamah. נמצא, Nimtza,
so in that case, עד זומם משלם ממון בעדות אחיו. Ed zomem
meshalem mamon b'edut achiv. So in this case, let's say everybody here
is proven to be a זומם. Zomem. Okay, everybody here is proven
to be a זומם. Zomem. So they now, all these four people
pay Michal for her plot of land because they all as a
group were basically trying to steal her land. Right. But now he's
got a problem. Brothers are paying on account of their other brothers.
Okay, so again what you see is is that this idea that
you can't testify with your brother doesn't mean that there can't be
a case where there's like an עד זומם Ed zomem issue because
you're not being, your, this testimony here, his testimony isn't against his
brother. These are distinct testimonies and the fact that he testified impacts
him. But that's not the prohibition against testifying together, okay, against testifying
against your brother.
אלא הזמה מעלמא קאתי. Ela hazamah m'alma ka'ati. You don't say that
in this case ראובן's Reuven testimony is against שמעון. Shimon. No, they're
being, you know, even though it was necessary for everybody to testify,
what's, what's making them pay, you don't say this testimony's making them
pay, with the other person's testimony. What's making them pay are the
עדים זוממים Edim zomemim that came in, or the מזימים Mazimim that
came and said you were all liars. Okay. הכא נמי הזמה מעלמא
קאתי. Hacha nami hazamah m'alma ka'ati. So here too it would be
the same. So just because these two guys can't testify against one
another doesn't mean they can't testify together against someone else. Even if
they're עדים זוממים Edim zomemim they'll have to pay. You don't say,
oh your testimony is against one another. No, you know, the עדים
מזימים Edim mazimim would have made you pay. But again, but that's
not testimony, you're not testifying against your co-עד. ed. So just because
they can't testify against one another is no proof that they can't
testify against a third party. So let's take a look. So אלא
אם כן, Ela im ken, so where were we? אלא אם כן.
Ela im ken. But how do we know just because they can't
testify against one another, they can't testify against a third party? So
it says אלא אם כן לכתוב קרא ובן על אבות. Ella im
kein lichtov kra uven al avot. אי נמי Ina nami הם על
אבות. heim al avot. מאי ובנים? Mai ubanim? Okay, so it could
have said, so it could have said לא יומתו אבות על בנים,
Lo yumtu avot al banim, okay, לא יומתו אבות על בנים Lo
yumtu avot al banim והם על אבות. veheim al avot. What did
it have to repeat the word בנים? banim? Okay? It already said
אבות על בנים ובנים לא יומתו על אבות. avot al banim ubanim
lo yumtu al avot. It could have just made it shorter: והם
על אבות. veheim al avot. So by adding the extra word ובנים,
ubanim, אפילו בנים לעלמא, afilu banim l'alma, that's to tell you that
not only can they not do it against one another, but even
any of these combined can't do it against a third party. You've
just gotta go with it. Somehow the extra word is allowing us
to say not only you can't do it against one another, but
you can't do it to a third party. Now,
עד כאן קרובי האב. ad kan krovei ha'av. Now all of that
is relationships through the father, which is consistent with the idea of
because it's אבות avot and משפחת אב mishpachat av and the, right,
in general before you get to the ירושה yerusha idea just in
general, primary family association is through the father, משפחת אב. mishpachat av.
And, you know, going to the earlier teaching, it's ראוי ליורשו ra'ui
leyorsho also, in the line of inheritance. And all of this the
פסוקים psukim talk about father,
okay. קרובי האם מנלן? Krovei ha'em minalan? How do you know that
it's, right, how do you know that Leah can't even testify here
against Leah's husband? What should we call Leah's husband? Shechem. No, not
Shechem, that was Dinah's husband. Yaakov. That was Dinah's that didn't even
merely her desire to have him. Anyway, I don't mean Leah, I
meant Dinah, excuse me, I meant Dinah. That's why, okay, okay, so,
okay.
So how did you know that it's not only against the father
and the father's brother, but even the father's sister's husband? Okay? So
where do you know to include, to include a mother in all
of
this? אשכחן Ashkachan קרובי האב. krovei ha'av. קרובי האם מנלן? Krovei ha'em
minalan? אמר קרא אבות אבות תרי זימני. Amar kra avot avot trei
zimnei. It says לא יומתו אבות על בנים ובנים לא יומתו על
אבות. lo yumtu avot al banim ubanim lo yumtu al avot. Why
didn't it say ובנים לא יומתו עליהם ubanim lo yumtu aleihem or
something like that? So the same way בנים banim was extra to
tell you they can't combine for a third party, the second אבות
avot is extra to tell you not only fathers, but even mothers,
okay. So תרי זימני. trei zimnei. אם אינו עניין לקרובי האב, Im
einu inyan lekrovei ha'av, since we don't need it
to tell you a father's relative because we already mentioned that, תנהו
עניין לקרובי האם. tenei'u inyan lekrovei ha'em. So that allows us to
get in a mother's relative, so it includes mothers. Okay. עד כאן
לחובה. Ad kan lechovah. Now this is to testify against them, so
against them יומתו, yumtu, to punish them. Okay. So therefore, you can—now
that's a little interesting given the way it's being read, you can't
punish... so we all know that when you're dealing with family, it's
like love-hate, right? But it's interesting that the primary reading here, if
you were to say why can't you testify against a relative
or on behalf of a relative, your immediate assumption would be that
you want to testify, you know, to help them, and we assume
that you're going to be biased to help them. But here, because
the פסוק pasuk says they shall not die, and we're not reading
this about sin, but we're reading this about testimony, the primary פסוק
pasuk is you can't testify against them. And, you know, and sometimes
we know that happens too with family, like, you know, you'd be
biased against them. So how do we know you also can't testify
on their behalf? So אשכחן לחובה, לזכות מנלן? Ashkachan lechovah, lizchut minalan?
אמר קרא יומתו יומתו תרי זימני. Amar kra yumtu yumtu trei zimnei.
It says לא יומתו אבות על בנים ובנים לא יומתו על אבות.
lo yumtu avot al banim ubanim lo yumtu al avot. Why doesn't
it just say, it could have said והם על הם veheim al
heim or something like that?
עליהם על עליהם? aleihem al aleihem?
Right. So why does it say יומתו yumtu again? אם אינו עניין
לחובה, תנהו עניין לזכות. Im einu inyan lechovah, tenei'u inyan lizchut. I
know you love that. I understand. What can I tell you? אשכחן
בדיני נפשות. Ashkachan bedinei nefashot. Now that's about capital crimes, right? Because
that's very weighty. And again, you know, this was a little bit
interesting we had the other day about sin, you know, maybe
somebody is פסול pasul for דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, but it comes
to something more weighty, דיני נפשות, dinei nefashot, you know, maybe they
could be כשר, kasher, they wouldn't lie about that. But here, that
was the case about sin. This was more about a status פסול,
psul, and by status פסול, psul, you know, the גמרא Gemara said
before יוחסין yuchsin and so on, so there's more of a reason
to think that we have narrower standards by דיני נפשות. dinei nefashot.
So maybe these are just פסול pasul for דיני נפשות. dinei nefashot.
Maybe by דיני ממונות dinei mamonot we shouldn't exclude them.
אשכחן בדיני נפשות, בדיני ממונות מנלן? Ashkachan bedinei nefashot, bedinei mamonot minalan?
How do we know to exclude them even in monetary cases? אמר
קרא משפט אחד יהיה לכם Amar kra mishpat echad yihyeh lachem משפט
השווה לכולכם. mishpat hashaveh lechulchem. One law, it's all equal. Of course
it's not true, it's not all equal, there are some people who
are פסול pasul for דיני נפשות dinei nefashot and not for דיני
ממונות. dinei mamonot. We'll worry about that then, but our general point
of departure should be that it should all be the same. Okay,
that is now that's the easy part. Okay, that's just the פסוקים
psukim that it's based on. Now we get to actually worry about
the actual relationships. So let's take a look. אמר רב אחא אמר
רב. Amar Rav Acha amar Rav. said רב Rav. *Rav*. אחי אבא
לא יעיד לי lo yaid li, *achi abba lo yaid li* my
father's brother can't testify for me, הוא ובנו וחתנו hu u'vno v'chasno.
*hu uveno vechatno* he
and his son and his son-in-law. Okay. He, my father's brother, my
uncle. My uncle can't testify against me, he and his son, my
cousin, and even my cousin by marriage.
Wait, who? אחי
אבא *achi abba*. What?
אחי אבא *achi abba*.
He can't testify against me. He can't. הוא ובנו *hu uveno* his
son can't testify against
me, right? And his, oh, his son-in-law. Oh, so you mean is
it his son's son-in-law or is it his brother-in-law?
שמעון Shimon *Shimon* brother-in-law?
No, שמעון *Shimon* son-in-law. If this is שמעון *Shimon*'s
daughter, okay, whatever her name will
be, so whatever, I can't come up with names. What? יוכבד *Yocheved*.
יוכבד *Yocheved*. Okay. And יוכבד *Yocheved* here is married to עזרא *Ezra*,
so that's his son-in-law. Okay. He also can't testify. My cousin by
marriage. Okay. So, okay, הוא ובנו וחתנו hu u'vno v'chasno. *hu uveno
vechatno*. אף אני לא *af ani
lo*—so that's in the משנה Mishna *Mishna*. Okay. But now he takes
another state. אף אני לא אעיד לו *af ani lo a'id lo*
I can't testify against him, my uncle. Okay. אני ובני *ani uveni*
not only can I not, but חנוך Hanoch *Chanoch*'s child cannot. Okay.
So, I don't know, we'll call him חיים *Chaim* to keep with
the ח *chet*. Okay. So, אני ובני וחתני *ani uveni vechatani* or
חוה *Chava*'s husband here, okay. What? אדם *Adam*. Okay. Okay. So not
only, not only the cousins and the cousin-in-law, which was the משנה
Mishna *Mishna*, but if you, because remember, the משנה Mishna. *Mishna* mentioned
this, and then the משנה Mishna. *Mishna* said they and their sons
and their sons-in-law. So that would be first cousins. But רב Rav
*Rav* says if you go by sons and sons-in-law of the uncle,
then you should go by sons and sons-in-law of the nephews. Okay.
So this means you can't testify for a great-uncle. Not just a
cousin, but a great-uncle. And this is a even a great-uncle-in-law. And
this is a שלישי בראשון shlishi berishon. *shlishi berishon*. Yup. So that
is the big מחלוקת *machloket* in הלכה Halacha *halacha* about how we
פוסק *pasken* about that. שני בשני sheni besheni. *sheni besheni* is פסול
pasul. *pasul*. Is שלישי בראשון shlishi berishon. *shlishi berishon* פסול pasul. *pasul*?
רב Rav, *Rav* says yes. הגמרא *hagemara*'s going to disagree with it.
רב Rav *Rav* says שלישי בראשון shlishi berishon. *shlishi berishon* is פסול
pasul. *pasul*. This thing here was not mentioned in the משנה mishna.
*Mishna*. Okay. So let's take a look at הגמרא *hagemara*. Okay. So
הגמרא *hagemara* says like this. ואמאי הוי ליה שלישי בראשון shlishi berishon,
*ve'amai havei lei shlishi berishon* a great-nephew to a great-uncle is a
שלישי בראשון shlishi berishon *shlishi berishon*. ותנן שני בשני sheni besheni תנן
*vetnan sheni besheni tnan* our משנה mishna *Mishna* only went up to
first cousins. שני בשני sheni besheni *sheni besheni*. שני בראשון תנן *sheni
berishon tnan* or an uncle, שני בראשון *sheni berishon*. שלישי בראשון shlishi
berishon לא תנן *shlishi berishon lo tnan* it did not deal with,
you know, a great-uncle, שלישי בראשון shlishi berishon *shlishi berishon*. So הגמרא
*hagemara* says no. Yes, I'm going to read this into the משנה
mishna. *Mishna*. How am I going to read this into the משנה
mishna, *Mishna*? מאי וחתנו דקתני במתניתין חתן בנו b'no *mai vechatno dekani
bematnitin chatan beno*. When our משנה Mishna. *Mishna* says
you
can't testify for your uncle or your uncle's son, it said it
said you can't testify for your uncle, talking about שמעון *Shimon*, and
then it said ובנו וחתנו *uveno vechatno*.
Right? That's what the משנה Mishna. *Mishna* said about שמעון *Shimon*. So
the way רב Rav *Rav* is reading this, הגמרא *hagemara*'s saying is,
it means ראובן Reuven. *Reuven*'s son, my cousin, and his son's son-in-law.
Okay.
So this, that's what he's reading into the משנה Mishna *Mishna*. It
doesn't mean his son and his son-in-law. It means שמעון *Shimon*'s son
and שמעון *Shimon*'s son's son-in-law. So the משנה Mishnah. *Mishna* is dealing
with a case of שלישי *shlishi*. Except the problem is is that
then it's a case of a, if you're looking at the chart
here, of a שני בשלישי *sheni beshlishi*. Do you see that? Because
משנה Mishnah. *Mishna* said I can't testify for my uncle, my uncle's
son, and the way רב Rav *Rav* is reading him, my uncle's
son's son-in-law, which is a שני בשלישי *sheni beshlishi*. רב Rav, *Rav*
did not go so far to say שני בשלישי *sheni beshlishi*. Okay.
So הגמרא *hagemara*'s going to reject this read, but for now that's
what we're forcing into a read of the משנה Mishnah *Mishna*. Okay.
So הגמרא *hagemara* says like this. מאי וחתנו דקתני במתניתין חתן בנו
b'no *mai
vechatno dekani bematnitin chatan beno*. ואי הכי בן בנו *ve'ei hachi ben
beno* if you wanted to go that far, why didn't they say,
you know, שמעון *Shimon*'s son and שמעון *Shimon*'s grandson? Why does it
say שמעון *Shimon*'s son's son-in-law? מילתא אגב אורחיה קמשמע לן דבעל כאשתו
*milta agav orchei kamashma lan deba'al ke'ishto*. No, that's even a bigger
חידוש *chiddush*. Even this much degree removed, right? My first cousin's son-in-law,
even that, even like a שני בשלישי *sheni beshlishi*, even through marriage,
if that were true, that would be a very, you know, distant
relation. Okay. So that's how we're reading the משנה *Mishna* in order
to support the idea of a third generation. So הגמרא *hagemara* says
one minute. והדר *vehadr* That but רבי חייא *Rebbe Chiya* teaches שמונה
אבות *shmonah avos*, if you count in our משנה *Mishnah*, there are
eight main categories of people that are פסול pasul. *pasul*. Okay, what
are the eight? Just to show you quickly.
שמונה אבות בנזיקין *shmonah avos b'nezikin*.
I know, it's very similar. Okay, you have brother, you have uncle,
brother, okay, brother, you have uncle, uncle who is directly father's brother,
uncle who is a father's sister's husband is three, uncle who is
a mother's brother, four, a mother's sister's husband is five,
where are the other ones?
Oh,
a father-in-law. Anyway, whatever, I don't want to go into it right,
I could count it later. But anyway, if you go through the
משנה *Mishnah*, there are basically eight people mentioned in the משנה *Mishnah*,
okay? And you'll take my word for it. Actually, there's nine and
we'll worry about it in a minute, but okay. For now, you'll
take my word for it. Anyway, there are eight. Okay, but he
says שמונה אבות שהן עשרים וארבע *shmonah avos shehein esrim v'arba*. Now,
if you have eight, but remember within the eight, we said of
all the people mentioned in the משנה *Mishnah*, let's say you did
uncle, we said בנו וחתנו *b'no v'chasno*. So if the משנה *Mishnah*
mentions eight people that are פסול pasul *pasul*, plus sons and sons-in-law,
that becomes, right, 24.
Got that? Okay, so we'll do the counting later. But he says,
but according to you, שהן עשרים וארבע *shehein esrim v'arba*. הני תלתין
ותרתין היין *hani tlaskin v'tartein hein*. But according to you, it's not
just limited to sons and sons-in-law. It would include another generation, right,
grandsons and grandsons-in-law. So it should be 24, it should be 32,
it actually should be 48, whatever. Anyway, that's not, so clearly that's
not how רבי חייא *Rebbe Chiya* is reading our משנה *Mishnah*.
Fine. אלא לעולם חתנו ממש *ela l'olam chasno mamash*. Let's reject that
read. That was a really bad read anyway. ומאי קרי ליה חתן
בנו *u'mai ka-rei lei chasan b'no*? כיון דמעלמא קאתי כדור אחר דמי
*keivan d'mei-alma ka-ati k'dor acher dami*. So he says fine, you're right.
פשט *pshat* in the משנה *Mishnah*
is
son-in-law. Okay, but nevertheless what רב Rav? *Rav* is saying is, is
that since the son-in-law
is not directly related to you, it's only sort of through marriage,
so it's effectively like another generation. Yes, you're right, the משנה *Mishnah*
is only talking about sons and sons-in-law. But once we're including sons-in-law,
you know, sons-in-law
is already pretty distant, so if you're going to include that, you
might as well also include a next generation. Okay, so it says
חתנו *chasno*, but as רב Rav, *Rav* says, you know,
still to support the second and third?
This is when רב Rav *Rav* said that when the משנה *Mishnah*
says חתן בנו *chasan b'no*, okay, he's really saying, let's read it
again. Yes, the משנה *Mishnah* is only talking to your son-in-law. So,
but why did רב Rav, *Rav* call it your son's son-in-law? To
tell you that the משנה *Mishnah*, once it's including son-in-law, is effectively
including a third generation. כיון דמעלמא קאתי *keivan d'mei-alma ka-ati*, he's not
really a blood relative, he's only married into the family, כדור אחר
דמי *k'dor acher dami*. Okay, so bottom line is fine, the משנה
*Mishnah* is only talking about these two, but somehow רב Rav *Rav*
still reads into the משנה *Mishnah*, if you can get to son-in-law,
then you can get to a third generation. But the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says but one minute, אי הכי הוה ליה שלישי בשני shlishi
besheni *i-hachi hava lei shlishi b'sheni*. If you're telling me that somehow
implicit in this משנה *Mishnah* is not only Shimon's son, but Shimon's
grandson, that's a שלישי בשני shlishi besheni. *shlishi b'sheni*. And רב *Rav*
never went that far. רב *Rav* only did a שלישי בראשון shlishi
berishon, *shlishi b'rishon*. Okay, so don't tell me that in the משנה
*Mishnah* רב *Rav* is reading in another generation.
אי הכי הוה ליה
שלישי בשני shlishi besheni. ורב הכשיר שלישי בשני shlishi besheni *i-hachi hava
lei shlishi b'sheni v'Rav achsher shlishi b'sheni*. For רב *Rav* שלישי בשני
shlishi besheni, *shlishi b'sheni* would be כשר kasher, *kasher*. So don't try
to read this in the משנה *Mishnah*. The משנה *Mishnah* is dealing
with שני בשני *sheni b'sheni*, it does not deal with a third
generation. But רב *Rav* didn't say
one way or the other about שלישי,
yeah, but he only mentioned the שלישי בראשון *shlishi b'rishon*. Implicitly שלישי
בשני shlishi besheni. *shlishi b'sheni* would be okay. אלא רב דאמר כרבי
אליעזר *ela Rav d'amar k'Rebbe Eliezer*. Fine, forget the משנה *Mishnah*. The
משנה *Mishnah* is only שני בשני *sheni b'sheni*. רב *Rav* says like
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, *Rebbe Eliezer*, דתניא *d'tanya*, taught in a ברייתא
*braisa*, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר *Rebbe Eliezer omer*, כשם שאחי אבא
לא יעיד לי lo yaid li, הוא ובנו וחתנו *keshem she-achi aba
lo ya'id li, hu u'vno v'chasno*, the same way my father's brother
can't testify against me, he and his son and his son-in-law, so
that's cousins. כך אחי אבא הוא ובנו וחתנו, כך בן אחי אבא
*kach achi aba hu u'vno v'chasno, kach ben achi aba*, my cousin,
לא יעיד לי lo yaid li, הוא ובנו וחתנו *lo ya'id li,
hu u'vno v'chasno*. So this ברייתא *braisa* of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer.
*Rebbe Eliezer* explicitly says my cousin's kids, okay, can also not testify
against נחשון *Nachshon*. Okay, and this will be נחמיה *Nechemya*, whatever, I
can't do the woman. No, נחמה *Nechama*, right, נחמה *Nechama* married to
John. Okay, whatever. Anyway, so the same way my cousin can't, my
cousin's sons and sons-in-law also can't. So he's explicitly going one generation
further but this is a שלישי בשני. shlishi besheni, This by the
way is first cousin once removed if anybody wants to know the
American nomenclature. Cousin's children are second cousins, שלישי בשלישי shlishi beshlishi is
a second cousin, שלישי בשני shlishi besheni. is a first cousin once
removed. Okay, so anyway he, רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, does go one
generation further. Okay, but again we've got a problem, that's going further
than רב. That's שלישי בשני. shlishi besheni רב only said שלישי בראשון.
Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says הוא ובנו וחתנו אהייא אלא אילימא הוא ובנו
וחתנו. hu uvno vechatano ahaya ela elima hu uvno vechatano. Okay, והא
קא הוי ליה שלישי בשני. veha ka havei leh shlishi besheni. Okay,
so רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer taking it to the point of a
שלישי בשני. shlishi besheni. And רב, רב implicitly was saying שלישי בשני's
okay, it's only שלישי בראשון. So רב סבר לה כוותיה בחדא ופליג
עליה בחדא. Rav savar lah kivateh bechada ufalig leh bechada. Fine. רב
is a midpoint between our משנה and רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer He
doesn't go as far as רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer excuse me, to
say שלישי בשני, but he doesn't but he does go as far
as say שלישי בראשון. Okay, so we have now here three positions.
Our משנה limits it to two generations, שני בשני. רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer, says even שלישי בשני. רב says a middle position, שלישי בראשון,
grand-nephew, great-uncle, no? Okay, so but he doesn't but שלישי בשני, first
cousin once removed, he would not say. Okay, so those are two
positions, רבי אליעזר and רב, that are more strict than our משנה.
Alright, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this, מאי טעמא דרב? mai taama deRav? Now what's motivating רב? דאמר
קרא, daamar kra, the verse says לא יומתו אבות על בנים ובנים,
lo yumtu avot al banim uvanim, the extra ו. vav. It could
have said לא יומתו אבות על
בנים בנים.
lo yumtu
avot
al banim banim.
Right, בנים ובנים בנים, banim uvanim banim, something like that. Their sons'
sons, right, the extra ו vav is so they can't die on
their sons and their, you know, meaning their nephews and their sons'
sons and their and their great-nephews. לרב לדרשא אחרינא. leRav ledrasha achreina.
Okay, ולרבי אליעזר ובנים אמר רחמנא. veleRabbi Eliezer uvanim amar Rachmana. So
the גמרא Gemara says and רבי אליעזר takes it one step further
because this ובנים, uvanim,
פסולי דאבות שרי אבנים. psulei deavot sharei abanim. The same way by
the father it extends to sons and sons-in-law, by the father's son,
here, the uncle's son, right, the cousin, it extends to the cousin's
sons and sons-in-law, and that would be a שלישי בשני. Okay, so
that's the end. Now how do we פסקן? pasken? So here's a
big debate. Nobody פסקנס paskens like רבי אליעזר, okay. But the רמב"ם
Rambam and what do you call it, if I'm remembering correctly, רמב"ם
Rambam and the רי"ף Rif פסקן pasken against רב, שלישי בראשון is
כשר, kasher. and the אשכנזים Ashkenazim פסקן pasken like רב that שלישי
בראשון is פסול. pasul. Okay, so obviously for אשכנזים Ashkenazim the general
rule is שני בשני is no-go, שלישי בראשון is no-go. The way
I tell my students to remember it is once you've got the
nomenclature down you can sort of figure it out is that anything
that is equal to the number four or less is פסול. pasul.
Okay, so שלישי בראשון, שני בשני is no-go, שלישי בשני would be
good. Okay, so basically it's first cousins and if we're going to
פסקן pasken like רב, it also includes great-uncles and great-nephews. Okay, and
then all the in-laws, alright. There are some cases where you don't
do אשתו כגופו, ishto kigufo, but the general default is to assume
that in-laws are included. Yes.
So the implication is ספרדים Sefardim would follow the רי"ף Rif and
the רמב"ם? Rambam?
Right. I believe that is how the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch פסקנס.
paskens. Yes. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: now another
case. Now we're going to deal with some more straightforward, haha, applications
of our משנה. I know. אמר רב נחמן, amar Rav Nachman, let's
see if we can get through this דף daf today. אמר רב
נחמן, amar Rav Nachman, אחי חמותי לא יעיד לי. achi chamoti lo
yaid li.
My mother-in-law's brother, okay, cannot testify for me. So my mother-in-law's
brother, so that would be my
mother-in-law, my wife's,
here, well here let's draw something else. Let me erase this.
Should I draw it again?
I will, we probably will, but whatever.
Okay, anyway, here's my mother-in-law's brother.
So what would be a good case? Okay, יצחק Yitzchak is married
to
רבקה, Rivka, okay, and wait, my mother-in-law's brother, בתואל. Betuel. No, that's
the father. That's the father, right, we
don't know the mother. Alright,
let's use some
complete unknowns. I don't know, use your family.
Okay. to my
family.
But רבי נחמן Rebbi Nachman himself...
I'm reading some fascinating books. So he's supposedly married
to ילתא Yalta with
some... who's her
father?
I don't know.
This is getting too complicated at this stage. Okay, fine. We'll use
my family, okay?
Don't tell my wife.
Okay, so it's on YouTube so probably won't...
it's okay, it's okay. Okay, that's my mother-in-law and her brother, now
I have to remember my mother-in-law's brother... what's his name? Harold. Okay.
Okay, so there we go.
You wouldn't know otherwise, you could just make up a name.
Yeah, but Deborah's going to watch this. Okay, anyway. Okay,
so where were we?
Okay, אחי חמותי, Achi chamoti, my mother-in-law's brother, לא יעיד לי, lo
yaid li, can't testify for me, okay? Because if you basically apply
the principle of אשתו כגופו ishto kegofo as it were, this makes
it like it's my mother, and this and so it's my mother's
brother. So we already know mother's brother can't testify, right? So that's
a case of the uncle. Okay, so this אשתו כגופו ishto kegofo
makes it basically my mother's brother, okay, לא יעיד לי, lo yaid
li, בן אחי חמותי ben achi chamoti לא יעיד לי, and his
son here, don't ask me my his son's names, actually I know
them but okay, anyway, his son can't testify because that's basically like
uncle's son, that's a form of first cousin, okay? Once you combine
for the marriage purposes, it's a type of a first cousin, right?
Okay. לא יעיד לי, בן אחות חמותי ben achot chamoti לא יעיד
לי, and the son of my mother-in-law's sister, okay,
is also a case of a first cousin. Whether it's a son
of her brother, son of her sister, it's basically a case of
a first cousin. So once you combine husband and wife, and once
you assume that it doesn't matter whether you're going through the father's
family or the mother's family, this is just a case of uncle
or of uncle and cousin.
First cousin for your kids, vis-à-vis your kids, right? I mean that...
right, that would be a שלישי בשני. Okay, ותנא תונא, vetana tuna,
and our תנא tanna teaches us as well, בעל אחותו... baal achoto...
ותנא תונא vetana tuna means basically furthermore?
No, תונא tuna is our תנא. tanna. התנא שלן, hatanna shelan, תנא
tanna the first תנא tanna is the verb. Our תנא tanna teaches.
And this is taught by our תנא. tanna. This is implicit in
our משנה. בעל אחות, baal achot, okay, a sister's husband, ובעל אחות
אביו, ubaal achot aviv, okay, so anyway let's just do it like
this way. Okay, you've got a brother,
sister, okay, and her husband. Okay, so the משנה says that's no
good, okay,
brother-in-law,
sister's husband. Okay, that's in the
משנה. ובעל אחות אביו ubaal achot aviv or, okay, my father's, okay,
father's sister's husband, yes, okay, ובעל אחות אמו, ubaal achot imo, and
my, so my father's sister's husband and ובעל אחות אמו, ubaal achot
imo, and my mother's sister's husband.
Mother's sister's husband, okay,
an uncle by marriage. הן ובניהן וחתניהן. hen uveneihen vechataneihen.
They and their children and their stepchildren. So if you have a
case here about their stepchildren, okay, this will be a case of
daughter
and husband. So that's in the משנה, right? So this is basically
a case of uncle and, you know, cousin, right? So what he
just said, which he took this case but he looked at it
from this perspective, from the perspective of this stepson, of the of
the son-in-law, did I say step I meant son-in-law, okay, they and
their children and their children-in-law. Okay, so that's a case of uncle
and cousin and cousin and
cousin-in-law. Let's not talk, yeah let's not talk about that. So looking
at it from the perspective of this husband, who is this? This
is his mother-in-law's, right?
You with me here? Right? His mother-in-law's, right, his wife's mother. His
mother-in-law's, from this guy's perspective. From this guy's perspective it's his uncle,
his uncle by marriage, his uncle's kids, cousins and his cousin's in-law.
But from this guy's perspective it's his mother-in-law's, his wife's mother, right,
you with me? His mother-in-law's sister's son. Okay, so it's the same
point. It's first cousin by marriage except the connection, the first link
through marriage starts at the very beginning rather than coming at the
end. Okay, so but once you combine them and they're one unit,
it's basically a case of a cousin. Okay, so... whether you're combining
the husband and wife at the end or at the beginning, it's
the same thing in the mirror image.
Okay, אמר רב אשי. Amar Rav Ashi. That was fun. Okay,
okay, אמר רב אשי. Amar Rav Ashi. כי הוינא בי עולא, Ki
havina be'Ulla, when I was in the house of עולא, Ulla, איבעיא
להו, iba'ya lehu, they asked a question. He asked the following question.
He asked the following: אחי חמיו מהו? Achi chamiv mahu? What about
my father-in-law's—so if we'll use this example—my father-in-law's brother? Okay, so
that should be pretty clear, that's the easier case. If my mother-in-law's
sister, whatever, my father-in-law's brother, right, it's another case of essentially uncle,
uncle through marriage. מהו? mahu? בן אחי חמיו מהו? ben achi chamiv
mahu? Or my
father-in-law's—I know, we're just going to—just another opportunity for us to show—spell
out the cases in the משנה. בן אחות חמיו מהו? ben achot
chamiv mahu? My father-in-law's sister's son, what is? So all these are
cases are like cousins by marriage. Okay, so אמר ליה, Amar lei,
תניתוה. tanituha. It's in our משנה. אחיו, Achiv, your brother, ואחי אביו,
ve'achei aviv, ואחי אמו, ve'achei immo, your—הן ובניהם וחתניהם. hen u'vneihem ve'chatnehem.
Okay, so they and their sons-in-law. So once you do the sons-in-law
and you work it back, it becomes my father-in-law's brother and my
father-in-law's brother's, you know, sister's son and so on. Okay, I'm not
going to draw it again, but it's basically the same point. These
are cousins and uncles by marriage. Okay, and it's just to sort
of starting it—don't put the חתניהם chatnehem at the end, the in-law
at the end. If you start it—you know, if you do the
mirror image, you start from the—then it's mother-in-law's brother, father-in-law's brother, and
so on. Okay, now, ובניהם וחתניהם, u'vneihem ve'chatnehem, fine.
רב איקא למיזבן גדילי. Rav Ika le'mizban gdilei. רב went to go
buy some קלפים. klafim. Why that's relevant I don't know, but an
interesting little color. גדילי גדילי. Gdilei gdilei. קלף. Klaf. קלף. Klaf. Okay,
בעי מיניה, Ba'ei minei, they asked him. מהו שיעיד אדם באשת חורגו?
Mahu she'ya'id adam be'eshet chorgo? Can a person testify against his stepson's
wife? Because here,
remember, the משנה said חורגו לבדו. chorgo levado. The one person,
here you go ahead and you
have—let's see, I don't know, you have
אברהם—no, Avraham who married somebody with children? You don't have a case
in the תורה Torah where somebody married somebody with children. Okay, anyway.
Oh yeah, you do, if you do like שמעון married דינה Dina
with children, according to the מדרש.
Midrash. Anyway, fine. Okay, but anyway, whatever. Okay, so it doesn't matter,
it doesn't matter. Okay, so we went for אברהם, Avraham, somebody else.
מרדכי Mordechai here married לאה Leah after she already had ראובן. Reuven.
Okay,
so it's a different—it's alternate history. יעקב Yaakov died first, and then
מרדכי Mordechai came and married לאה, Leah, she already had ראובן. Reuven
It's a stepson, okay, no blood relationship at all. Okay,
and he's just like married
to—to, you know, to her. Okay, and then, so חורגו לבדו. chorgo
levado. So ראובן's, Reuven you know, kids, חנוך Hanoch. or whatever, he
would be כשר. kasher He could be testified to him because, you
know, this is like—he only relates to him because he married the
mother. So he actually would be כשר kasher. to go ahead and
to testify against חנוך. What about ראובן's wife?
Do we say that חורגו לבדו chorgo levado doesn't go to another
generation, but it would include the wife because of a type of
אשתו כגופו? ishto k'gufo? Or would it really only be the stepson
himself? Okay, so that's the question. So, okay, they asked
him a
question. מהו שיעיד אדם באשת חורגו? Mahu she'ya'id adam be'eshet chorgo? בסורא
אמרי בעל כאשתו. Besura amri ba'al k'ishto. Yes, it's no good, even
though it doesn't go down another generation by stepson. Okay, it does
go—it does apply to wife based on the אשתו כגופו ishto k'gufo
principle. הבעל
כאשתו. haba'al k'ishto. בפומבדיתא אמרי אשה כבעלה. BePumbedita amri isha k'va'alah.
So the one you normally hear in הלכה halacha is אשתו כגופו,
ishto k'gufo, right, the woman is subsumed into the man. But it
is interesting that the first version of it has it in the
reverse: בעל כאשתו. ba'al k'ishto. Okay, which would mean I guess it
would include my daughter-in-law's husband, right, my
son-in-law—I mean my stepdaughter's husband and my stepson's wife, those would be
פסול. pasul. They're considered one unit.
So בסורא beSura and פומבדיתא Pumbedita they agree?
They're agreeing, just different ways of formulating it. דאמר רב הונא אמר
רב נחמן De'amar Rav Huna amar Rav Nachman or אמרי אמרי רב,
amri amri Rav, מניין שאשה כבעלה דכתיב: minayin she'isha k'va'alah de'chtiv: ערות
אחי אביך לא תגלה, ervat achi avicha lo tegaleh, אל אשתו לא
תקרב. el ishto lo tikrav. Do not expose the nakedness of your
father's brother, do not draw close to his wife. דודתך היא, dodat'cha
hi, she's your aunt. והלא אשת דודו היא. ve'halo eshet dodo hi.
But it's not your aunt, it's your—it's your uncle's wife. And so
what does it mean why is that exposing the nakedness of your
uncle? It's exposing the nakedness of your uncle's
wife. מניין... minayin... The wife would still be included. Okay, and אשה
כבעלה isha k'ba'alah and בעל כאשה ba'al k'ishah is sort of a
general principle about all of these because basically as I said it's
uncles and cousins including sort of in-laws through marriage. All right. Okay,
so now it says like this. ובעל אמו, U'va'al imo, okay, ובעל
אמו U'va'al imo הוא ובנו וחתנו.
Ruben and the wife are no good. You're just making sure I
understood that, right?
So Mordechai cannot testify for Ruben's wife but Ruben,
but Ruben, or Ruben can't or their children.
Yeah. Okay. All right. ובעל אמו ובנו, U'va'al imo u'vno, okay, ובעל
אמו U'va'al imo is mother's again husband is הוא ובנו וחתנו. So
so
he and his sons and his sons-in-law. So this is mother's husband.
Now if mother's husband is you know is basically a stepfather, right?
Assuming that it's not your father then it's a stepfather. Okay now
בנו היינו אחיו. b'no hainu achiv. Now when it says
so actually this is a good example okay mother's husband okay he
and בנו so which son? The son that Mordechai has here with
Esther? Okay
you know is that is that is that the brother? Okay so
when it says he and בנו so the son that is not
at all there's no blood relationship at all right? It's a son
through a separate marriage. We're assuming not that way. We're assuming it's
gotta be some relationship. It's gotta be a son that Mordechai here
has with לאה, Leah, okay so Liam we'll call him. Okay
so if it's that son so then then it's already Ruben's brother
through his mother, right? So we don't have to say that that
son is פסול. pasul That's a brother. Okay so the גמרא Gemara
says בנו היינו אחיו אמר רבי ירמיה לא נצרכה אלא לאחי האח.
B'no hainu achiv amar Rabbi Yirmiyah lo nitzrecha ela l'achi ha'ach. No,
no, no. We're dealing, we are dealing with this son that he
had from Esther, okay? Somebody who basically is no blood relationship at
all. Okay but assuming that he had a he had a he
had a son with with with Ruben's mother, the relationship goes sort
of through. It's like we share a mother okay and they and
these two share a father, right? Do you see that? Okay. So
therefore it's Ruben's brother's brother. To Ruben it's nothing, no shared father
or mother, but it's Ruben's brother's brother. Would that be included? Okay.
So that's what we're saying. Yes, when it says his son, it
does mean this person that has no relationship to Ruben but now
one assumes that one wonders does there have to be a son
here in order to make the jump? Okay. It sounds like it
does, but assuming there's a son here he's פסול psul because it's
his brother's brother. Okay. So אמר רבי ירמיה לא נצרכה אלא לאחי
האח. Amar Rabbi Yirmiyah lo nitzrecha ela l'achi ha'ach. רב חסדא אמר
אחי האח Rav Chisda amar achi ha'ach רב חסדא Rav Chisda says
that's כשר. kasher. Your brother's brother, your half brother's half brother
you know that you have no relationship to is כשר. אמרו ליה
לא שמיע לך הא דאמר רבי ירמיה. Amru lei lo shamia lach
ha d'amar Rabbi Yirmiyah. Didn't you hear that? No, that's what Rabbi
Yirmiyah says is the case in the משנה. Stepfather's son they say
is the case of brother's brother and that's פסול. אמר להו לא
שמיע לי. Amar lehu lo shamia li. No, I didn't hear that
interpretation of the משנה. כלומר לא סבירא לי. K'lomar lo sevira li.
Which really means like that's what my wife says my problem is.
It's not that I don't hear, it's that I don't listen. Okay,
so anyway fine. לא סבירא לי. Lo sevira li. I don't hold
of that. I don't read the משנה that way. I don't think
that a brother's brother is a problem. אי הכי היינו אחיו. Ei
hachi hainu achiv. So if we're talking here about Liam that's your
brother. So why did it have to mention your stepfather's son if
it's also your mother's son? That's your brother. Why did it have
to mention that? So תנא אחי מן הא ותנא אחי מן היא.
Tana achi min ha v'tana achi min hi. Yeah okay but it's
just being explicit to again mention this idea that women are part
of this whole equation that the same way a brother through a
father is a brother, a brother through a mother is a brother.
Fine. אמר רב חסדא Amar Rav Chisda says רב חסדא Rav Chisda
אבי
חתן ואבי כלה מעידים זה על זה. Avi chasan v'avi kallah me'idim
zeh al zeh. Okay the
the what's it called the מחותנים mechutanim can testify against one another.
The parents of the the father of the bride and the father
of the groom okay which is right? So that's so all right.
So so that's a case where right? Is that a
הלכה
or is it like a discussion up for discussion now?
What? Is it a discussion up for discussion now? Or is it
like?
Up for discussion?
Or is it like?
I'm sorry.
Well let's see. Well let's see where we go. Okay.
Okay so these are the
חזון איש Chazon Ish אשתו כגופו ishto k'gufo or the
בעל ואשתו כגופו. ba'al v'ishto k'gufo. Right.
Right. If you do אשתו כגופו ishto k'gufo that it sort of
it's
true. So
Yeah, I mean, it's true. This becomes like this person's father, right?
So they can't testify because this is like this person's father. But
you can't sort of be, but the father slot is already taken.
So what are you supposed to sort of like be here? Like,
you know, I mean you want to say just sort of like
brothers, you know, but like, but to themselves, right. Yeah, it's an
interesting idea once you're sort of saying the אשתו כגופו, ishto kegufo,
you're right. If it's my son's father, how can I testify to
somebody who's my son's father? But I can't actually consider it my
son's father because that's me, right? So let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. All right. Also, I think I pointed out once before
that it's interesting, right, which languages have words for מחותנים. mechutanim. Like,
I think that certain, like,
in Spanish I think there's a word for it. It speaks about
certain, you know, the ways in which
society sees those as, you know, relationships that are going to be
sustained, you know, and that's type of a sort of a grouping,
yeah?
In Arabic there's a different word for the uncle through the mother
and the
uncle through the father.
Oh, interesting. Because of this?
Okay, interesting.
Okay, so the two fathers can testify against? Yes. So let's just
finish the two dots because we're already a little bit over.
So it says like this. Okay.
מינים זה לא, minim ze lo, ולא דמו להדדי, v'lo damu lahada,
אלא כחלא לדנא, ella ke'achla ledana, and they're not related to one
another except like a cover on a pot. And the way the
ערך Arech explains it, it means not like a tight-fitting cover, like
a loose cover on a pot. Yeah, they're, they're related through their
kids, but it's not a close connection. So therefore they can מעיד
meid against one another. Okay. So אמר רבה בר בר חנה: Amar
Rabba bar bar Chana: מעיד אדם לאשתו ארוסה, me'id adam leishto arusa,
a person can testify about his wife who's only the קידושין, kiddushin,
not yet the נישואין. nisuin. Okay. We're going to reject it. אמר
רבינא: Amar Ravina: לא אמר אלא לאפוקי מינה, lo amar ella lafuki
minah, that would only be against her interest, to say that she's
losing a case because then it's hurting your own interests, because you're
going to marry her and that money won't be coming into the
marriage. אבל לעיילו לה, aval le'ayilu lah, to help her, bring money
into her, you know, into her, so לא מהימן, lo m'heman, you're
not believed, because then you're helping your own interests, right? The גמרא
Gemara says: ולא היא, velo hi, but you know what that's not
true. לא שנא לאפוקי ולא שנא לעיילו, lo shna lafukei velo shna
le'ayilu, it doesn't matter whether you're hurting her, whether you're helping her,
לא מהימן, lo m'heman, you're not believed. She's still your betrothed even
if you're not yet married yet. מאי דעתך? mai da'atach? What, why
did you think to make this distinction? כאמר רבי חייא בר אמי
ke'amar Rabbi Chiya bar Ammi משמיה דעולא: mishmei de'Ulla: אשתו ארוסה, ishto
arusa, לא אונן lo onen ולא מטמא לה. velo mitame lah. We
have all these הלכות halachas before the נישואין, nisuin, that even though
halachically it's the wife because you haven't been living together, so if
it's a, you know, if she dies the person doesn't sit שבעה,
shiva, ולא מטמא לה. velo mitame lah. If it's a כהן cohen
and not an אונן, onen, he's not אסור assur in קרבנות. korbanos.
If it's a כהן cohen he doesn't become טמא tamei to her.
וכן היא לא אוננת ולא מטמא לו, v'chein hi lo onenes velo
mitame lo, same if he dies. מתה אינו יורשה, meisa eini yorashah,
if she dies he doesn't inherit her yet because again they haven't
yet consummated, it's not yet the נישואין. nisuin. מתו, meisu, if he
dies however גובה כתובתה, gova kesuvatah, she still does collect her כתובה.
kesuva. That is the one thing that still applies anyway. So you
saw there that there were this ways in which she wasn't yet
the full wife. התם בשארו תלה רחמנא, hasam beshe'eiro tala rachmana, that's
because it says כי אם לשארו הקרוב אליו, ki im lishe'ero hakarov
eilav, who a כהן cohen is מטמא mitamei to. When it comes
to inheritance it says לשארו הקרוב אליו ממשפחתו. lishe'ero hakarov eilav mimishpachto.
שאר she'er means like flesh. Only once they've basically slept together to
become like one flesh, one unit, and do all those הלכות halachas
apply in terms of inheritance and טומאה tumah and all those things.
Okay, בשארו תלה רחמנא. beshe'eiro tala rachmana. ואכתי, ve'akti,
ואכתי לאו שאר היא, ve'akati lav she'er hi, and before they've had
the נישואין nisuin it's not שאר. she'er. הכא משום איקרובי דעתא הוא,
hacha mishum ikruvei da'ata hu, but here it's because you know you
have a close relationship, it's because you know you're inclined towards the
person, sometimes because of their behalf, sometimes you know you're so close
that you maybe want to דווקא davka hurt them, you know, but
it's ultimately about
connection. והאי איקרובי דעתא גבה, ve'hai ikruvei da'ata amgabah, and this woman
that you're eventually going to do נישואין nisuin and you already have
אירוסין, erusin, obviously you're connected to, and therefore clearly it's going to
be פסול. But what it is interesting is after all of these
things we've identified that this reason is איקרובי דעתא. ikruvei da'ata. But
the important thing to know which was implicit but I'll just end
by making this explicit as opposed to discussions earlier about like, you
know, if you do this type of a sin we're afraid that
that'll mean that you can be bribed and that you'll testify falsely
and it was sort of connected and even there we saw that
some was a status פסול. Any עבירה aveira you get מלקות malkus
even if there's no concrete concern you'll testify falsely makes you a
רשע. rasha. So here too, even if we acknowledge that in the
background here's a concern that if you're related that might influence your,
your testimony, at the end of the day as the גמרא says:
משה ואהרן, Moshe ve'Aharon, that we would never suspect their testimony of
being biased, they still can't testify together or against one another. It
doesn't matter how much somebody is beyond any
doubt and, and can be, you know. Now and so on once
whatever is part of the reasons behind it in a formal way
these relatives are just פסול and it doesn't matter how much we
are or not in fact really concerned about influence. But here it
seems interesting trying to identify this issue of the wife and which
whether the betrothed wife is or is not included we are influenced
by this reason of איקרובי דעתא. ikruvei da'ata. But once we put
somebody in that category we don't make any case-by-case decisions. You know
we don't so once somebody is in that category it's a formal
status פסול and it's not based on whether concretely there is a
concern that their testimony will be influenced or not. Okay well then.